All right!
（相生祐子(あいおいゆうこ)）よーし
Here goes!
じゃあ いくぞ
じゃんけん
Rock, paper, scissors!
ぽん
あっちゃー
Okay!
（長野原(ながのはら)みお）
よっしゃ  じゃあ 私からね
I'll be starting, then.
P-i-ne-app-le-s!
じゃんけん
Rock, paper, scissors!
ぽん
よーし　いくぞ
All right!
Here I go!
You can't do that!
ダメだよ
１段ずつってルールじゃん
The rule is to go up one step at a time.
I know!
分かってるって
Gu... ri... co... bonus!
…の おまけ
お… おまー！
H-Hey!
Heh?
えっ 何？
What is it?
何 勝手に付け足してんの？
Why are you putting that at the end?
Eh?
えっ？ 普通
おまけって付けない？
You don't normally put "bonus" after it?
What do you say, Mai-chan?
ねえ 麻衣ちゃん
（水上麻衣(みなかみまい)）
フィフティ フィフティ
Fifty-fifty.
I get it.
（みお）
分かった それでいいよ
It's fine like that.
But if you're going to do that,
ただし そっちがそうくるなら―
then I'll put my own rules into effect, okay?
私も自分ルール 発動させるからね
Rock, paper, scissors!
（３人）じゃんけん
ぽん
You're next, then, Mai-chan.
（祐子）
よっ 次は麻衣ちゃんだね
chi-yo-ta ni-ke-ra ha-to-ho ra-su-te no-ha-te ki-ra-to na-ri-ha shi-te-to
ち  よ  た―
に  け  ら　は  と  ほ―
ら  す  て
の  は  て　き  ら  と―
It's the spell for revival.
復活の 呪文…
It stopped.
止まってる…
Argh, Mum, I told you to wake me up at seven!
もう お母さん！
“７時に起こして”って
言ったじゃん
Mum!
お母さん！ あっ
TL note: sepak takraw - kick ball
Dear Mio,
I'm off to to the sepak takraw game with the
people from the neighbourhood association.
.                                             From, Your Mother
Sepak...
セパ… セパタクロー
...Sepak takraw.
Nichijou 05
Argh.
ああん もうっ
Even though I'm on day duty today.
今日 日直なのに
（みお）
目覚ましも 目覚ましだよ
Setting the alarm clock aside,
why did they have to cut the power today, of all days?
なんで 今日にかぎって
電池切れちゃってるの？
Really, I wish they'd warn us in advance if they're going to cut the power!
まったく
切れるなら 切れるって
先に教えてっての
This sucks!
この スカポンタン！
I'll just have to hammer out the fastest lap that I can.
（みお）とにかく
最速ラップを たたき出すの
That should be enough to...
そうすれば なんとか…
I mean, just now...
（みお）…というか 今
（みお）ものすごいのいた！
There was something freaky there!
Above that...
しかも なんか…
It's coming!
（みお）来たあ！
う… うわっ あっ おわっ
What what what what!?
（みお）なに なに なに？
このスプリンター
This sprinter!
Why... is it... following me!?
なんで 私を… 追って…
Impossible!
抜いた！
（みお）ハア ハア ハア
（かぶり物少女）フウッ
Um... Excuse me...
（少女）あのう… すみません
木魚 落としませんでした？
Did you drop a wooden mask?
Or maybe a golden one?
金の木魚ですか？
It'll get me.
（みお）やられる
If I don't do it,
やらなきゃ やられる…
it'll get me.
I'm sorry!
すいませんでした
（少女）プフッ
Sometimes, I'm a bear.
あるときは クマ
And sometimes...
そして また あるときは…
...I'm a b-ea-r...
して その正体は…
Whose identity is...!
（少女）ご… ごめん ごめん
S-Sorry, sorry.
（長野原(ながのはら)よしの）ジャーン
Tada!
正解は お姉ちゃんでした
The answer was your sister!
You didn't realise I was wearing the
same school uniform as you, did you?
みおの学校の制服着てたから
分かんなかったでしょう
Ah, that was fun-
ああ 楽(たの)…
Oh, that is a fine corkscrew this early in the morning.
（紳士）ほーお
これは朝から
見事なコークスクリューじゃ
Yes.
（付き人）いやあ
すばらしいですよ 実に
It is indeed splendid!
It was a lot of work, you know, to stop your alarm clock as well.
いや いやあ 苦労したんだよ
目覚まし止めるのも
大変だったし
You were the culprit?!
（みお）お前が犯人かっ！
No, no, no.
いや いや いや
そんな怒んないで
Don't be so mad.
Here, I'll treat you to some ramen with this.
ほらっ これでラーメン
おごるからあ
That was my pocket money!
それ 私の野口！
chi-yo-ta ni-ke-ra ha-to-ho ra-su-te no-ha-te ki-ra-to na-ri-ha shi-te-to
ち  よ  た―
Spell
に  け  ら　は　と―
ほ　ら　す  て
の  は  て　き―
Chiyota
Nikera
Hatoho
Rasute
Nohate
Kirato
Nariha
Shite
Please enter your revival spell:
The spell is wrong.
Nichijou 06
んん？ ああ サメ
A shark...
A shark!
サメ
I'm home!
（東雲(しののめ)なの）ただいま
Hm?
あれ？ はかせ
何してるんですか？
Professor, what are you up to?
なの　あの雲 サメっぽい
Nano!
That cloud looks shark-ish!
Heh, which one?
（なの）へえ どれですか？
Ah, it really does!
ああ ホントですね
It looks cool.
カッコいいね
Indeed it does.
そうですね
Ah, yeah.
あっ そうだ
はかせ
買ってきましたよ 牛乳
I brought it with me, Professor.
Milk.
ウフッ
Is it the 4.5?
（はかせ）ねえ 4,5　4,5
The 4.5?
The 4.5 milk?
Yes, it's the special one.
はい　特濃ですよ
But what happened?
The 4.5 milk~
でも どうしたんですか？
急に牛乳 飲みたいなんて
For you to want to drink milk so suddenly...
エヘッ それはね
That is...
Because there's cake roll!
（はかせ）
ロールケーキがあるからあ
うまっ うまっ うまっ うまっ
…って なに勝手に
改造してるんですか？
Why are you remodelling me without asking!?
Because it's a cake roll.
（はかせ）ロールケーキだから
（なの）意味が分かりません
I don't understand!
Nano, the 4.5 is milk!
なの　4,5 牛乳
It's not 4.5!
“4,5”じゃないですよ！
なんで 腕にロールケーキ入れて
生活しなきゃいけないんですか？
Why do I have to live with a cake roll in my arm!?
（はかせ）プハーッ
It's cold and delicious!
ちゅめたくて おいちい
I'm not talking about that!
（なの）
そういう問題じゃありません
もう こんなところ
外で誰かに見られたら…
What if someone outside saw this?
戻るう
（はかせ）うまっ うまっ
うまっ うまっ　んんっ
くう… プハーッ
Professor...
はかせ
なあに？
What is it?
Um... Can I have some, too?
あのう… 私にも少し
Okay.
いいよ
わあ
Just a minute.
（はかせ）ちょっと待ってね
（なの）ウフッ
Here, go ahead.
はい どーぞ
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございます
（はかせ）
うまっ うまっ うまっ うまっ
（はかせ）うまっ ハア
（なの）あ… あのう…
Um...
Hm?
A little of that cake roll, too?
ロールケーキのほうも…
あっ そうだ
Ah, yeah!
I'll give the sweet bun to you, then, Nano.
じゃあ なのは甘食ね
Eh!?
Go ahead.
（スイッチを押す音）
（はかせ）どうぞ
（なの）戻った
It went back in!
（はかせ）あっ ごめんね
Sorry, I pressed the wrong one by mistake.
間違って押しちゃった
（スイッチを押す音）
（なの）ひいっ
So, why are you doing these things?!
だだ… だから なんで
こういうことするんですか？
何かのはずみで
外で作動したら―
What would I do if it happened outside,
どうなると
思ってるんですか？
because of a bump of some sort?
どうなるの？
What will happen?
きっと…
I'm sure...
Commander Sunborn Master is the greatest!
（客１）コマンドサンボマスター
最高だよな
Right!
（客２）だよね
（なの）痛っ　あっ
（客１）うあっ
（客２）ええ…
I'll also make it so you can play music!
音楽再生機能も付けとくね
That's not the point!
そうじゃないです
How did this become about remodelling me even more?
なんで 改造していく方向に
なってるんですか？
（はかせ）うんっ　プハーッ
Listen to me properly, please!
ちゃんと聞いてくださいよ…
（はかせ）ごくっ ぐっ ぐっ
This much!
この一杯！
うぐぐー ああ…
（なの）もう…
あーむ
プハーッ
あっ 何ですか？
What is it?
Sweet bun!
甘食…　ヘヘッ
You can't have it, since you already ate the cake roll.
ダメです
はかせは もうロールケーキ
食べたんですから
あーむ
（なの）
あっ あれ？ はかせ？
Eh?
Professor?
いいもん！
It's okay,
since I still have some Baumkuchen left!
なぜなら まだ―
バームクーヘン
あるから！
Eh, eh?
N-No way.
ま… まさか！
今度はどこから？
Where will it come out this time?!
Above?
上？ 下？
Below?
ああっ ガビーン
P-Put them all in the refrigerator the first time, please!
さ… 最初から全部
冷蔵庫にしまっておいてください
（はかせ）ヤダ！
（なの）ええ！
No!
Eh?
Shinonome Institute
Eh...
First comes rock, next comes paper, rockscispaper doesn't count,
（はかせ･なの）
♪ 最初はグー  その次 パー
rock paper scissors!
（はかせ）もぐ もぐ もぐ もぐ
（なの）ううっ
I'm so sleepy...
眠かった
（祐子）みーおーしゃん
Mio-san.
What's that smile for?
何？ その笑顔
Show me your notes!
ノート見せて
Don't tell me you forgot your homework, again?
まさか また宿題 忘れたの？
いやあ お恥ずかしいかぎりで
It's pretty embarrassing...
（みお）もう そんなんだと
また試験で痛い目 遭うよ
Geez.
If you keep that up, you're in for a
painful experience on your exams again.
I get it.
分かってるって
But this time, only for this time...
今回… 今回だけ
I'll make this the last time, so please.
最後にするから お願い ねっ
How about it?
Yukko.
（みお）ゆっこ　この前も
同じこと言ってたでしょう
That's what you said last time, too, isn't it?
There's no "last time" in ignorance!
武士に二言はない！
No, I told you before...
（みお）いや だから
すでに言ってるんだってば！
えっ　そ… そっかあ
Eh...
I-Is that so?
（みお）ハアッ
Oh, well... I guess there's nothing we can do.
もう しょうがないなあ
Just this once, okay?
今回だけだからね
I mean it.
ホントだからね
I get it.
分かってますって
One should always treasure their Mio-chan.
持つべきものは みおちゃんです
Yukko!
（吾妻(あがつま)）ゆっこ
さっき言ってたの出てきたよ
The one I told you about has appeared!
I'll give it back as soon as I've copied it.
（祐子）
じゃあ 写したら すぐ返すね
Sure.
Really?
（祐子）
本当？ 見せて 見せて
Show me, show me!
Huh?
（みお）あれ？
Am I forgetting something?
何か 私 忘れてない？
Last night, I did my homework...
昨日の夜 宿題 終わって…
I did my homework...
宿題 終わって…
（男）そう
I drew...
（みお）何気に描いた…
（男）だって…
I drew a picture in there...
何気に描いた 絵
...and forgot about it by this morning!
（みお）消すの忘れてた！
I won't
let you
do it.
I won't
let you.
I won't let you do it!
（男）そうはさせんぞ
I forgot!
忘れてた！
Nichijou 07
Right? Right?
（吾妻）でしょ でしょう？
Yeah!
だねえ
（みお）ゆっこ
（祐子）あっ　ん？
Yukko!
Sorry, sorry.
いやあ ごめん ごめん
そういや私も宿題 忘れててさ
Come to think of it, I forgot to do my homework.
It beat me!
いやはや まいった まいった
So that means, I'm taking my notebook back.
…というわけで
ノートは返してね
ごめんね
Sorry.
Eh?
What?
何？
See, there's no point in looking...
だから 見てもしょうがな…
また またあ
もう そういうのやめてよ
Again?
Don't say that.
You said you'd lend it to me.
次は やってくるって
言ってるじゃん
I'm off.
ごめん　お待たせ
Sorry, I'm back now.
This is bad.
（みお）マズい…
This is very bad.
マズいぞ これは…
あんな絵 見られたら
確実に変な目で見られる
If she sees that, she'll definitely think I'm weird.
Not to mention, if she sees that...
しかも その絵を見るのが
よりによって ゆっこ
Especially if it's Yukko, she'll definitely tell...
その伝達力は…
（祐子）
いやあ ハッハッハッハッ
（みお）音速！
...everyone!
ふんっ
（みお）ゆっこ！
（祐子）ん？
Yukko!
T-That's my Japanese notebook.
そ… それ
国語のノートだったよ
This one's my maths notebook.
数学のは こっち…
But this one's got "Maths" written on it.
でも これ“スーガク”って
書いてあるけど…
うっう
You're wrong!
ちちち… 違うの！
It hurt... my stomach hurt!
い… 痛かったの！
おなかが痛かったの！
Okay.
（祐子）あ… うん
（みお）ギャン
Oh no.
I'll copy it right away.
じゃあ すぐ写しちゃうから
ちょい待ってて
Hold on for a bit.
（みお）終わる…
Oh no.
If she sees it now...
ここで見られたら 終わる…
...it's over.
My high school life will be...
私の高校生活が…
...over.
終わる…
Yukko.
（みお）ゆっこ！
That notebook... I'll buy it from you for 1000 yen!
そのノート 千円で買った！
Why are you running away?!
なんで逃げるの？
Yukko!
ゆっこ！
You've got it all wrong.
違うの そのノートは…
That notebook is... That notebook is...
そのノートは―
...going to explode!
爆発するの！
It's useless.
（みお）無理だ
There's no way I can chase down the running Yukko.
走って ゆっこに
追いつけるはずがない
終わる… 私の人生が…
It's over.
My life is...
ありがとう 私の人生
Thank you, my life.
Up until now it has been fun.
今まで楽しかった
There were a few bad things, but it was a happy life.
ちょっぴり
イヤなこともあったけど―
総じて 幸せな人生だった
But now it's over.
でも 終わり…
My life is over...
私の人生は終わるの…
...along with my banquet of men.
男たちの うたげと共に―
It's over.
終わり…
Like. Hell. I'd. Let. It. Be. Over!
…にするわけにはいかない！
My life is blazing!
命を 燃やせええー！
Coconut
Milk
ええいっ
Even so, I still can't reach her.
（みお）それでも 届かない…
Yukko!
ゆっこ　廊下は―
Don't... run in the hallway!
走るなあ！
ハア ハア ハア ハア
Are... Are you all ri-
ちょ… 大丈夫？
Here.
はい
Okay, hand your notes in from the back.
（赤城(あかぎ)先生）
じゃあ 後ろからノート集めろ
After that, those who didn't do their homework, own up quickly.
あと 宿題を忘れたやつは
早く名乗り出ろ
（みお）フウッ
（みお）一時はどうなることかと
思ったけど
An hour ago, I was wondering how I'd go on,
なんとか事なきを得て よかった
but it looks like I managed to survive just fine.
With this, my everyday life has returned...
これで私の何気ない日常が
戻って…
Ah!
I didn't erase it!
（みお）消してない
（男）やあ
What is it, Naganohara?
どうした？ 長野原
Our Goal: Sweat Buckets And Enjoy Youth Together
Sensei!
（みお）
先生　宿題 忘れました！
I forgot to do my homework!
...and like this.
（なの）こうしてっと
Tidying Up
Professor, can you help me clean up some of the mess in this room?
はかせ　ちょっと部屋のゴミ
片づけてもらっていいですか？
It might be a bit soon for the Professor.
はかせには まだ
ちょっと早いかもしれない
I'm going to go play.
（はかせ）遊んできます
（なの）あの…
Um...
I said to that guy...
Student Guidance
Um, excuse me.
（桜井(さくらい)先生）あのっ すみません
Annaka-san, can I have a moment?
安中(あんなか)さん　ちょっと いいですか？
（安中）あっ はい？
Yes?
（桜井）ああっ いえ…
It's just for a moment.
ちょっとだけなんですけどね
That ribbon, I wonder if it's a bit too big...
そのリボン
大きすぎるかなあ… なんて
Pyon~
ピョン なんて
Sweet Buns
（はかせ）あむ あむ あむ
甘食もおいしいね
Sweet buns are delicious, aren't they?
Indeed they are.
そうですね
（はかせ･なの）あーむ
TickMart
Welcome!
（店員）いらっしゃいませ
Sold Out
Home-Style
Sweet Bun
55 Count
Super
Full of
vigor
Super
Manager's Choice
Adult Flavor
Super
Delicious
Cheap Sweet Bun
55 Count
Nichijou 08
（立花(たちばな)みさと）ハア…
Sasahara, do you have any sense of responsibility as a Cultural Festival Executive Committee member?
笹原(ささはら)
あんた文化祭実行委員としての
自覚あんの？
You need to think seriously about it.
もう少し真面目に
考えたらどうなのよ
I am utterly diligent.
（笹原幸治郎(こうじろう)）
私は至って真面目だ
I'm the President of the Drama Club, so I'm always like that.
演劇部 部長として
常に役に備えているのだ
Do you not even understand that, Tachibana Misato?
そんなことも分からんのか？
立花みさとよ
No, I don't understand it!
分かんないわよ！
Sweet.
（笹原）甘い
（みさと）聞け
Listen to me!
Besides, we're here to decide on the program for the cultural festival.
大体 ここは
文化祭の出しものを決める場
Your Drama Club has nothing to do with it!
あんたの演劇部は
関係ないでしょう？
The brand has changed?
銘柄が変わったか…
ハア…
Why did I end up paired together with this guy?
なんで こいつと
一緒の組になっちゃったかなあ
It's delicious.
美味である
ああ 私だって
剣道部の大会近いんだからね
Even I've got a tournament coming up in the Kendo Club...
Geez.
まったく 文化祭の実行委員なんて
やるんじゃなかったわ
I shouldn't have joined the Cultural Festival Executive Committee.
ウフッ
Hey, you!
ちょっと あんた！
Why are you reading manga?
なに マンガなんか読んでんのよ！
If we don't come up with something quickly,
さっさと 案 出さないと
帰れなくなるじゃない
we wont be able to return home.
Sorry.
（笹原）
すまん　新刊だったものでな
It's a new release.
Don't you even have one idea?
１個ぐらい アイデアないの？
Was the wine tasting championship idea I gave you earlier really not any good?
先に挙げた―
“利きワイン選手権”では
ダメなのか？
Obviously, it wasn't any good.
ダメに決まってるでしょ！
却下よ　却下
ド却下よ！
Rejected. Rejected! Absolutely rejected!
Hey, Sasahara?
ねえ 笹原？
ちょっ… あんた
さっきから何なのよ！
You!
What have you been doing since earlier?
Sorry, had some piled up stuff.
（笹原）すまん
少し煮詰まったものでな
Analog signal...
あ… なんてこと
（みさと）
ああっ 笹原 ドロンする気？
Sasahara, running away, huh?
I'm going to make a brief trip to the toilet.
（笹原）
トイレへ はせ参じてくる
Honestly...
（みさと）まったく
（笹原）フンッ
It looks like she's in a really bad mood today.
今日は相当 機嫌が悪いようだ
As far as it concerns me,
私としては
利きワイン選手権で―
the wine tasting championship would have been more than enough.
十分だと思うのだが
Nevertheless, she didn't bring up any ideas of her own.
しかも あいつは
最初から全然 案を出さん
If I tell her that, this time she may even take my life.
あまつさえ それを言ったら
今度は命すら取られかねん
In other words,
すなわち 私が案を出さんと―
if I don't come up with something it seems I won't be able to go home.
帰れそうにないということか
However, can my way of thinking drop to the level of a commoner?
しかし…
思考を庶民レベルまで―
落とせるものなのか…
Maybe I should try thinking seriously about it.
まあ 少しは真剣に考えてみるか
べつに あんたなんか
何とも思っていないんだから！
I-It's not like I have feelings towards you.
Word of
Asian innocence.
the Day
This is a sweet bun.
（甘食）甘食です
関西ではマイナーらしく―
In Kansai, there seem to be many people who don't
know whether to read it as "Amashoku" or "Kamshoku"
“あましょく”と読むのか
“かんしょく”と読むのかも―
分からない人も
いっぱい いるらしいですね
Next week's Nichijou is the third one.
次回の「日常」は
第３話です
Narration:     Ikeda Masako
お楽しみに
Look forward to it.